The Papers of Georg and Max Bredig
Science History Institute
The Papers of Georg and Max Bredig
Bulk 1894-1944
2019.011
21.0 Linear Feet (30 Boxes and 213 Books)
Science History Institute
The collection consists of two discreet series of records. Series I consists of items created or collected by Georg Bredig, while Series II contains items created or collected by Georg's son, Max. The collection is arranged into the following series:
Georg Bredig was born in Glogau, (modern day Poland) in 1868, to a German Jewish family. He began his University education in 1886, first in Freiburg and soon after in Berlin where he studied chemistry and physics. In Berlin, Bredig was first introduced to the, which had been founded that very year by the eminent chemists Wilhelm Ostwald and Jacobus van't Hoff. Bredig was so enthusiastic about this new border science, that he transferred to the University of Leipzig to study physical chemistry directly under Ostwald, whose Institute had become the world's leading center in the field. Bredig excelled in his studies and earned the coveted spot as Ostwald's student assistant. Bredig earned his doctorate "summa cum laude" in 1894, and spent the next 18 months studying physical chemistry with some of the leaders in the field: first in Amsterdam with van't Hoff and afterwards, in Stockholm with Svante Arrhenius, with whom Bredig developed a life-long friendship. After a year and a half of studying abroad, Bredig returned to Leipzig to work as the Assistant to Ostwald. In this role, Bredig produced a series of pioneering works on colloidal metals and their catalytic properties and most notably developed a method for the preparation of colloidal solutions by use of an electric arc. He expanded on this work by studying and comparing the activity of metal colloids and that of inorganic ferments, which he summarized as his habilitation thesis in 1901. These successes led to his appointment as the first professor of physical chemistry at the University of Heidelberg. Here, he continued to develop his research from Leipzig and most notably achieved the first catalytic synthesis of asymmetric carbon compounds. In his personal life, Georg married Rosa Frankel in 1901. Together they had two children; a son named Max Albert, born in 1902, and a daughter Marianne, born a year later. In 1910 Bredig moved his family to Switzerland where he had accepted a professorship in the Physical Chemistry Laboratory at the ETH Zurich, but left soon after when given the opportunity to succeed Fritz Haber as Director of the Institute of Physical Chemistry at the Technical University of Karlsruhe. Bredig's appointment at Karlsruhe was initially accompanied by great public recognition. In 1914 he received the honorary prize of the Solvay Institute, and in the same year received the Knight's Cross from the Grand Duke of Baden, and an honorary doctorate from the University of Rostock. Among Bredig's students at Karlsruhe was Elizabeth Rona, who would go on to become a renowned nuclear chemist. In her autobiography, she described Bredig as "very much the authoritative German professor" who was known as, "Bredig the Terrible" by his students. But she added that, "under his surface sternness and aloofness, Bredig was a warm and sensitive person devoted to his students' welfare." World War I brought research in Bredig's lab to a halt. Bredig, a self-proclaimed pacifist spent the war as a University Administrator and volunteer for the Red Cross. His voluminous correspondence with Arrhenius reveal many of his other political attitudes which included support for the creation of a European Union to avoid future calamities like the Great War. These beliefs, however drew the unwanted attention of Nationalists and anti-Semites, who even in the 1920s would make Bredig the target of personal attacks. When the National Socialists seized power in 1933, anti-Semitic attacks against Bredig intensified. One of Bredig's employees wrote to the Ministry of Education and demanded Bredig's immediate resignation so as to, "put an end to the internationalization and socialization at German Universities." Then, the Nazi government passed the Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service, which, with some short-lived exceptions, banned all Jews from teaching at German Universities. Without fanfare, Bredig was retired on October 1, 1933. A short time later Bredig received another terrible blow, the death of his wife. Friends encouraged Bredig to leave Germany and continue his career, but he refused, as he found it hard to accept that he had actually become a victim or that the current situation was anything but temporary. Writing to a friend in 1933, he stated, "I still hang on my step-father country and consider emigration to be a serious misfortune." Prior to the outbreak of war, every day seemed to bring new regulations that restricted some aspect of Jewish life. Commenting on these restrictions Bredig wrote, "I am not allowed to step into the library anymore, nor my beloved public gardens." Later he writes "these days we must surrender all of our gold, silver and jewelry. For me only the sentimental value is painful… life nowadays is just so hard." Although, Georg still did not want to leave Germany, he frequently encouraged his son Max to do so. Max had been raised in Karlsruhe and followed in his father's footsteps by becoming a chemist. He obtained the equivalent of a master's degree from Karlsruhe in 1925, and then went to Berlin where he earned his doctorate under Fritz Haber. Upon graduation, Haber wrote a letter of recommendation on Max's behalf, stating, "Max rates among the most intelligent and best trained young colleagues I have met. Not easily will anyone be found who surpasses him in industry and thoroughness, good will and professional interest." When the Berlin firm where Max was working was Aryanized in 1937, Max heeded the warnings around him and left Germany, first going to Sweden, and then England, before finally joining his father's brightest pupil, Casimir Fajans, at the University of Michigan. Later Max moved to New York where he worked for the Vanadium Corporation of America. But more importantly, as the only emigrated member of his family, he worked tirelessly to rescue his father, as well as his sister Marianne, and her husband Viktor Homburger from the fate awaiting them in Nazi Germany. The atrocities of Kristallnacht hit particularly hard in the city of Karlsruhe. Georg, his son-in-law Viktor and about 500 other Jews in the city were arrested, beaten and publicly humiliated. Viktor's family bank was ransacked, and later confiscated by the state. Georg was forced to spend a day standing in a stable with his head against a wall. Although Georg was released the next day, Viktor was sent to the Dachau concentration camp. He was imprisoned for six weeks and only released after proving his intention to immigrate. After Kristallnacht, it was no longer a question of whether to leave Germany, or when to leave, but only how to leave, and this was not at all clear. Viktor had obtained quota numbers for American Visas, but the numbers were high. It could be years before it was his family's turn to emigrate. Certain that events in Germany would only get worse, Marianne insisted that her three step-sons be sent out of Germany as quickly as possible. To do so, Peter, Wolfgang and Walter who were 10, 12 and 14 years old respectively, were sent to live in England as a part of the famed Kindertransport in which 10,000 Jewish children were taken in by families across the United Kingdom. The events of Kristallnacht also convinced Georg that living out the rest of his years in Germany was not going to be possible. Georg managed to emigrate to the Netherlands in 1939 and from there joined Max in America, which became possible only when Princeton University offered Georg the position of Research Associate. Georg, thrilled to receive the appointment, sent his reply to the president of Princeton in a wonderfully short and succinct telegram, which read, "highly honored. Accept. Coming as soon as possible." He arrived in the United States just months later. In October of 1940 Marianne and her husband Viktor were still waiting for their chance to emigrate, when they, along with 11,000 other Jews from the Baden region of Germany, were forcibly deported to Vichy France. They were brought by train to Lyon, and then sent to the Gurs camp in Southwest France, which had been built years earlier for refugees from the Spanish Civil War. The camp commandants at Gurs were all French, and although they were at times described as friendly, they had no means to help the 11,000 people in desperate need of food, water and clothing. At first, the camp was only loosely a prison as individuals were permitted to leave so they could try to obtain food or secure their release by obtaining the proper travel permits. Marianne used this time to visit Viktor who was kept in a separate camp for men, and also, to send numerous letters to her father and brother. The collection holds many letters written by Marianne while she was interned at Gurs. They provide a unique description of daily life inside the camp, as well as insight into her own personal strength. Early on she wrote to Max, "As long as the sun shines, it is bearable here. If it rains and gets cold, it is quite terrible. What people here are suffering cannot be expressed. The poverty is unbelievably huge." She continues, "We could relieve a lot of the suffering of the people of Gurs if we could organize a sponsorship for people who receive no outside assistance. This kind of help is not just a question of money but more of taking on the responsibility. It is a question of empathy, of participating in the suffering of your fellow humans in the battle against apathy of the heart. We know of what many do for their relatives that are left behind. In addition, thousands should help unknown thousands." Max was in fact able to arrange many shipments of food and clothing to the camp. He accomplished this by wiring cash payments to a contact in Portugal, who would in turn send shipments of non-rationed dry goods to the camp in France. When Max was also able to arrange his sister and brother-in-law's release by securing their visas and arranging their transport to the United States, Viktor sent word to Max: "I cannot find words to express my gratitude for all you have done for us these last 7 months. Without your generous help dear Max, we would have never been able to escape the big misery in which we found ourselves. Our situation has often been very desperate, and the indescribably generous and huge help that you have given us has helped us to survive this most difficult time in our lives." Viktor and Marianne were the lucky ones. Of the 11,000 Jews evacuated from Baden and sent to Gurs, only about 1,000 were released. Approximately 1,000 others would die in the first winter in the camp, and many of the remaining were sent to death camps in Poland where they were not heard from again. In New York, the Bredig family finally reunited in 1941. Marianne found work as a seamstress and Viktor took a job as an accountant for the nonprofit group Self Help of Emigres from Central Europe. They were reunited with their three boys in 1945. Georg never quite regained his strength after immigrating and would never take up his passion for physical chemistry again. He died in New York on April 24, 1944 and was buried in Westchester County. Max spent the rest of the war working to help Jewish friends stranded in Europe and had a great many successes and some very tragic losses. He married Lydia Levy in 1944. After the war Max went to work at Oak Ridge National Laboratory where he served as Associate Director of the Chemistry Division. He died in November of 1977.
None.
The collection, which remained in the Bredig family until 2018, was inherited by George Bredig after the death of his parents. Upon discovering a trove of historic material, George arranged for the collection to be sold through a Pennsylvania based autograph dealer, The Raab Collection. The Institute purchased the collection in April 2019, with proceeds generously donated by the Walder Foundation. The Walder Foundation is a private family foundation based in the Chicago area dedicated to addressing critical issues related to Science Innovation, Jewish Life, Immigrant Advocacy, sustainability, and the performing arts.
Ernst Berl Papers, Science History Institute Archives, Philadelphia, PA. Ernst Berl Papers, United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, Washington, D.C. Kasimir Fajans Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI. Svante Arrhenius Papers, American Institute of Physics, New York, NY.
- Series I: Georg Bredig Papers, I
  Series I is comprised of the Papers of Georg Bredig. It includes both a correspondence and subject file related to his personal life and career as a physical chemist.
  - Series I: Sub-Series II: Georg Bredig Subject File
    This sub-series contains manuscript items (not including correspondence) that were collected and saved by Georg Bredig. Items include newspaper and magazine clippings, book prospectuses, certificates, scientific notes and diagrams and broadsides. It is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Bibliothek der Technischen Hochschule zu Karlsruhe - Check-out slips, (22 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 11
    - Apparatus for Electrical Dispersions - Diagrams
      Graphic Materials box 3 folder 7
    - Einstein, Albert - Etched Portrait of Albert Einstein by Lionel S. Reiss, circa 1921
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 1
    - Einige Versuche an Metallkristallen (Some Experiments on Metal Crystals), circa 1925
      Text box 3 folder 28
    - Scientific Notes and Diagrams apparatus, undated
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 7
    - Karlsruhe Library - List of Chemistry Journals, undated
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 25
    - Technical Physics of the USSR - Journal Prospectus
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 16
    - German Newspaper Clippings - Pertaining to Debye, Einstein, Curie, Ostwald, Nernst, Cohen, Haber et al. (24 items)
      Text box 4 folder 14
    - German-Russian Journal of Science and Technology, No. 9
      Text box 4 folder 15
    - Jewish Laws - German Newspaper clippings
      Text box 4 folder 24
    - Autographed Dinner Menu - Includes Fritz Pregl, Ernst Cohen, Jean Luc et. al.
      Text box 3 folder 9
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm - Handwritten draft of biography of Ostwald written by Georg Bredig. Contains scientific notes on the reverse, undated
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 37
    - Scientific Notes on the Planck Scale, circa 1921
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 12
    - Colloid Platinum Katalysis Poisoning, circa 1909
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 20
    - Jewish Immigrant's Aid, The Blue Card
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 23
    - Broadside - Commemoration of Lavoisier
      Graphic Materials box 3 folder 16
    - Acta Physicochimica U.R.S.S.
      Text box 3 folder 2
    - Scientific Notes which were housed within the pages of Physikalisch Chemisches Praktikum (20 items)
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 11
    - Haber, Fritz - Obituary
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 17
    - Notes on scrap papers - miscellaneous topics (38 items), undated
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 35
    - Gas Warfare - Clippings
      Text box 4 folder 9
    - Einstein, Albert - German Newspaper Clippings - Pertaining to Albert Einstein
      Text box 4 folder 2
    - Identification Papers - German Passport, Immigrant ID Card - United States, German ID Card, Declaration of Intention to become US citizen, and German Travel Permit
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 20
    - Prolog to the Concert of the rectors with invitation - Karlsruhe Technical University, 1923 June
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 42
    - Die Werksfackel - Newsmagazine
      Text box 3 folder 23
    - Certificates - Academic appointments and diploma, 1914, 1911
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 19
    - A Professor's Theory and It's Practical Uses, The Work of J. Willard Gibbs
      Text box 3 folder 1
    - Linde Ice Machine - Diagrams (printed), undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 29
    - Pfeffer, Wilhelm - Printed image, undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 38
    - German Newspaper Clippings (24 items)
      Text box 4 folder 13
    - Advertisement/Prospectus - Handbook of Applied Physical Chemistry in Individual Presentations, vols. I-XIV, published by Georg Bredig, undated
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 4
    - Dissertations in the Department of Chemistry at Karlsruhe Technical University (15 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 26
    - Notebook - Notes taken by Georg Bredig on the lectures of Herman Mark on Atomic Models and Wave mechanics
      Books box 4 folder 32
    - Scientific Notes and Correspondence which were housed within the pages of Dissertations from Bredig's Lab, vols. I-IV. Includes list of Bredig's doctoral students (23 items), circa 1930
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 6
    - Colloid Silver Therapy - Correction to treatment, undated
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 21
    - Loose Journal Covers and book prospectuses
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 30
    - Bibliothek der Technischen Hochschule zu Karlsruhe - Recent acquisitions
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 12
    - German Electrochemical Society - Goals for restructuring the society, circa 1902
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 12
    - Bredig, Georg - Obituaries (12 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 15
    - Scientific Notes, Clippings, Correspondence and annotated page proofs which were housed within the pages of Anorganische Fermente (50 items)
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 5
    - Bodenstein, Max - Bio sketch by Ralph Oesper reprinted from the Journal of Chemical Education
      Text box 3 folder 13
    - Notebook - Scientific notes taken by Georg Bredig, undated
      Books box 4 folder 33
    - Influence de la Temperature du Refrigerant surles mesures cryoscopiques by F.M. Raoult, Handwritten Manuscript
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 21
    - Scientific Notes which were housed within the pages of Einfuhrung in Die Mathematische Behandlung (31 items)
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 9
    - Report on the work of Otto Warburg on Catalysis
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 3
    - Invitations to Physical Chemistry Seminars and Colloquium
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 22
    - Dipole Measurements by the Dilute Solution Method, together with handwritten diagrams and tables, undated
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 24
    - Folders used to house Diplomas and Visa material, includes inscriptions by Georg Bredig, circa 1939
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 8
    - Scientific Notes of Georg Bredig written on the reverse side of memos from the Karlsruhe Hochschulvereinigung
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 8
    - Notes taken by Georg Bredig on C. Oppenheimer's work, "Die Fermente und Ihre Wirkungen", circa 1925
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 34
    - Printed Images of scientists - Includes Cohen, Gibbs, Ramsey, Planck, Bunsen, Arrhenius, van't Hoff, Pasteur, Becqerel, et. al. (40 items), undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 41
    - Dissertations in the Department of Chemistry at Karlsruhe Technical University
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 27
    - Scientific Notes and book prospectus which were housed within the pages of Kristalle und Rontgenstrahlen
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 10
    - Advertisements/Prospectus - Assorted scientific books (1 of 2) (87 items), 1905–1939
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 5
    - Advertisements - Laboratory supplies and apparatus (17 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 3
    - Stereographische Projektionsbilder der 32 Kristallklassen - Poster
      Graphic Materials box 5 folder 15
    - Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists - "Doctor Einstein's Mistaken Notions," An open letter from four Soviet scientists v. "A Reply to the Soviet Scientists" by Albert Einstein
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 3
    - Report on activity of the Institute for Physical Chemistry and Electrochemistry written by Georg Bredig
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 1
    - Hanbuch der Allgemeinen Chemie, volume I, Die Chemischer Literatur und die Organisation der Wissenschaft
      Text box 4 folder 18
    - Bibliography cover pages, (37 items)
      Text box 3 folder 10
    - Reports on the theses of Bepin Chandra Kar and Tarapada Bandyopadhyay
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 2
    - Fajans, Kazimierz - Page-proofs of work by Fajans, with annotations by Georg Bredig (30 items)
      Text box 4 folder 6
    - Georg Bredig - 1868-1944 - In Memoriam by Werner Kuhn
      Text box 4 folder 10
    - Engravings of famous scientists collected by Georg Bredig (includes, Wohler, Dalton, Berzelius, Berthollet, Liebig, et al.) (17 items), undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 4
    - Memorandum - The New Nitrogen Prices
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 31
    - Directory of Diplomas and Technical Work in Chemistry conducted at Karlsruhe Technical University (12 items), circa 1925
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 25
    - Bredig, Georg - Bio sketch by Ralph Oesper reprinted from the Journal of Chemical Education
      Text box 3 folder 14
    - Deutsche Chemische Gesellschaft - Membership Certificate
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 22
    - Schwartzman, Professor - Practical Exercises in the Use and Application of Polarization Microscopes, undated
      Text box 5 folder 4
    - "Katalyse" - Page proofs annotated by Georg Bredig (26 items)
      Text box 4 folder 26
    - Calling Cards of Bredig Colleagues - Collected by Georg Bredig (21 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 18
    - Reichsfluchtsteuer (Reich Flight Tax), Notes on Income, circa 1938
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 43
    - Financial and Insurance documents with scientific notes on the reverse (24 items)
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 7
    - Bunsen, Robert - Printed portrait, undated
      Graphic Materials box 3 folder 17
    - Application for Certificate of Identification (U.S.) with affidavit in support of immigration visa by Max Bredig (21 items)
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 8
    - Observational Results of Practicum on Optics "Beobachtungsresultate aus dem Praktikum uber Optik", undated
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 36
    - Exhibition Catalog - Herbst-Ausstellung 1926
      Text box 4 folder 5
    - Advertisements/Prospectus - Assorted scientific books (2 of 2) (84 items), 1905–1939
      Mixed Materials box 3 folder 6
    - Scientific Notes on the works of Max Planck, Fritz Haber and Richard Nernst, undated
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 13
    - Scientific Notes on the work of R. Abegg, undated
      Mixed Materials box 5 folder 14
    - La Nomenclatura Chimica Periodico Mensile Internazionale
      Text box 4 folder 28
    - Photographs of microscopic slides which were housed within the pages of Einfuhrung in die Metallographie, undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 40
    - Koenig, A. - Electrochemistry notes, undated
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 27
    - Photographs (miscellaneous scientific and landscapes), undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 39
    - Haber, Fritz - Caricature, undated
      Graphic Materials box 4 folder 16
    - Handwritten List Georg Bredig's colleagues - (Includes Cohen, Bodenstein, Arrhenius, Berl, Horiba, Mark, Oesper, Polanyi, etc. al.)
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 19
    - German Bunsen Society for Applied Physical Chemistry - List of formulaic characters
      Mixed Materials box 4 folder 11
  - Series I: Sub-Series I: Georg Bredig Correspondence File